

# Soohwan Kim

#### ALRESEARCH ENGINEER · SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

6-10, Seokye-ro 13-gil, Nowon-gu, Seoul, Rep. of KOREA

□ (+82) 10-4564-4668 | 🗷 kaki.brain@kakaobrain.com | 🏕 blog.naver.com/sooftware | 🖸 sooftware | 🛅 hwan-kim

"Try your best rather than be the best"

# Summary.

Current AI Research Engineer at Kakao Brain. I majored in Electronic & Communication Engineering and minored in Data Science at university. My research interests include technologies for human-machine interaction, such as automatic speech recognition, speech synthesis, and natural language processing. I enjoy software development and sometimes like to write my knowledge or thoughts. I want to be helpful to others through open source. You can check my github (http://github.com/sooftware) to see what I am currently up to.

## **Education**

#### **Kwangwoon University**

Seoul, South Korea

MAJOR B.E. IN ELECTRONIC & COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING / MINOR B.E. IN DATA SCIENCE

Mar. 2014 - Feb. 2021 (Expected)

- Major GPA: 3.90 / 4.5 / Total GPA: 3.70 / 4.5
- Courses: Capstone Design I-II, Al & Speech Signal Processing, Software Design, Computer Architecture, Operating System, Data Structure & Algorithm, Data Mining, Network Programming, IoT System Design, C programming, Basic Electronic Circuit Experiment I-II, Circuit Theory I-II, Engineering Math I-II, Digital Logic, Phisics Electronic Technology, Object-Oriented Programming, Object-Oriented Programming Practice, Digital Signal Processing, System Programming, Electronic Circuit Experiment I-II, Data Communication, Computer Network, Probability and Irregular Signaling Theory, Development Open-Source Software, Mobile Programming, Big Data Language, Big Data Processing & Application, Database, Statistical application

#### Career\_

Kakao Brain

Al Research Engineer Nov. 2020 - Present

- Research & Develop Speech and NLP fields
- Participation in NLP library development (Named Pororo)

**Kakao Brain** Pangyo, Gyunggi

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

- Research & Develop English, Korean and Chinese Speech Recognition models
- Multilingual Text-To-Speech model development (10 languages)

#### Spoken Language Lab (Sogang Univ.)

Mapo, Seoul

Aug. 2018 - Present

Aug. 2020 - Nov. 2020

Pangyo, Gyunggi

Undergraduate Researcher Apr. 2020 - Aug. 2020

- Research End-to-End Automatic Speech Recognition Models
- · Research Real-time Speech Recognition Based on Kaldi Toolkit

Technical Blog Naver Blog

• Technical posting of deep learning, programming, signal processing, paper review etc.

- Having more than 100 subscribers and an average of 200 visitors a day
- Blog Link

## Research Interests\_

Automatic Speech Recognition, Speech Synthesis, Natural Language Processing

Software Development, Software Architecture

Voice Activity Detection, Speech Enhancement, Cross-lingual

## **Publication**

2020 End-to-End ASR Models in English, Korean and Chinese, Bachelor's Graduation Thesis

2020 KoSpeech: Open-Source Toolkit for E2E Korean Speech Recognition, arXiv pre-print

November 14, 2020 Soohwan Kim · Résumé

# **Project Experience**

#### **Multilingual Speech Synthesis**

Kakao Brain

Oct. 2020 - Nov. 2020

DIRECTOR

• Development of a speech synthesis model that supports 10 languages

• Supports for Voice-Cloning and Code-Switching

#### **English, Korean and Chinese ASR Models Development**

Kakao Brain

Aug. 2020 - Oct. 2020

• Development of English, Korean and Chinese Wav2vec 2.0 Models

- Experiment for improving the speed of inference
- · Comparative experiment on accuracy / inference speed by output-unit such as Character, Grapheme and Subword

KoSpeechKwangwoon UniversityTEAM LEADERJan. 2020 - Aug. 2020

• Open-Source Toolkit for End-to-End Korean Speech Recognition

- Recorded the performance of the model at 10.31 character error rate
- Got more than 100 stars on the GitHub site.
- GitHub / Technical Report

DIRECTOR

# **Extracurricular Activity**

NLP Paper Reading

Kakao Brain

GROUP MEMBER Sep. 2020 - Present

- · Kakao Brain Natural Language Processing Team's weekly paper reading study
- Discuss the content of the thesis and record it on this link

#### **Deep Learning Principle Study Group**

Kwangwoon University

Jan. 2020 - June. 2020

- GROUP MEMBER
- Joined a study group studying basics of deep learning with mathematics.
- Implemented nodes from scratch using numpy and pandas, read papers
- Study audio signal processing.

#### **Speech Recognition Study Group**

Kwangwoon University

Jan. 2020 - Mar. 2020

• Study speech signal processing (Spectrogram, Mel-Scale, MFCC etc ..)

• Review of the paper on speech recognition record it on this link

## Skills

**GROUP MEMBER** 

Programming Python, Java, C/C++, Shell Script, SQL, Android, Arduino, Assembly, HTML

Deep Learning PyTorch, Fairseq, PyTorch Lightning

Data Analysis Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, NLTK

# **Honors & Awards**

#### **AWARDS**

2020.11 **1st Place**, Kwangwoon Engineering Festival (President's Award)

2020.11 People's Choice Award, Kwangwoon Engineering Festival

2019.10 **12th Place**, Naver A.I Hackathon - Speech

2019.09 Finalist, Kwangwoon University software start-up idea contest - Fall

2019.04 **People's Choice Award**, Kwangwoon University software start-up idea contest - Spring

2018.08 Excellence Award, Samsung Multi-Campus in Java-based Algorithm for SW Development

#### **Honors**

2020.01 School Representative, 5G-based ICT Convergence Service Idea Contest

2020.03 Excellent Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship

2019.03 Excellent Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship

2019.03 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University

2018.09 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University

2018.03 Academic Excellent Scholarship, Kwangwoon University